Guide to the James H. Karales photographs, 1953-2006 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
James H. Karales photographs 1953-2006 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Karales, James H.
18 Linear Feet Approximately 15,000 Items
Noted American photojournalist who worked for LOOK magazine; resident of New York, N.Y.
The collection spans the years 1953 to 2006 and houses a nearly-complete photographic archive of photojournalist James Karales, active from the 1950s to the 1980s. The majority of the images in the collection originated from Karales' documentary work for Look magazine during the 1960s. His major projects include images from Rendville, Ohio, a coal mining town and one of the first racially integrated towns in Appalachia; Vietnam during the war; New York's Lower East Side; Oregon logging; and individuals and events of the Civil Rights movement during the 1960s, housed in three inter-related groups - the Martin Luther King, Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), and Civil Rights Series. Other smaller projects include images of California, New Mexico, and other subjects. Formats in the collection include contact sheets, which serve as a thumbnail guide to almost all of the prints and negatives in the collection; black-and-white proof prints and finished prints ranging from 8.5x14 to 16x20 inches; original negatives (closed to research use); and over 1100 color slides. There are also many print materials and some correspondence and audiovisual materials. Acquired by the Center of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Research Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James H. Karales photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 2004-2009, with additional photographs received as a gift from the Gary Davis Collection in New York City in 2008, 2011, and 2012.
Biographical Note
James H. Karales was born in Canton, Ohio in 1930. In 1955, Karales graduated from Ohio University with BFA in photography. Upon graduation, he began a mentorship with W. Eugene Smith, who at that time was printing his Pittsburg photographs. Karales learned printing skills under Smith, while pursuing his own projects in Rendville and the Pacific Northwest. In 1960, he joined the staff at Look magazine, where he worked until it ceased publication in 1971. At Look, he took some of his most iconic pictures, documenting Martin Luther King, Jr., the Selma to Montgomery civil rights march, Vietnam and the Lower East Side. Karales receieved numerous awards, such as the Overseas Press Club Award and the Picture of the Year. His photographs are housed in many collections including the International Center of Photography, the High Museum, and the Museum of Modern Art.
Chronology List
1930 July 15 Born in Canton, Ohio
1955 Graduated from Ohio University with a Bachelor of Fine Arts; Became darkroom assistant to photographer W. Eugene Smith
1955 Cleveland Plain Dealer Pictorial Magazine published Ohio Sub Hunters by James Karales
1956 Journeyed to Rendville, Ohio for documentary photography shoot
1958-1959 Edward Steichen purchased two Rendville, Ohio prints for Museum of Modern Art; Helen Gee exhibited Karales' Rendville photographic essay at Limelight Gallery, Greenwich Village; Traveled to the Pacific Northwest to document logging practices and culture
1960 Joined the staff of Look magazine
1962-1963 Photographed Martin Luther King Jr. and his followers in the civil rights movement
1963 Look published The New New York: Victims of Welfare by Sam Castan, with images by Karales
1964-1967 Traveled twice to South Vietnam, capturing images from the Vietnam War
1965 Look publishes What Johnson Faces in South Vietnam by Sam Castan, with images by Karales
1965 Photographed the Civil Rights march from Selma to Montgomery Ala.; Won award for Pictures of the Year.
1965 Look magazine published Our Churches’ Sin Against the Negro by Robert W. Spike, with images by Karales
1966 Look magazine published Saigon: Stained Pearl of the Orient by Sam Castan, with images by Karales
1969, 1975, 1985 Photojournalistic work on the Lower East Side, New York City
1971 Look magazine folded; Karales launched career as independent photographer
1999 First major solo gallery exhibit at Howard Greenberg Gallery, New York City
2002 Apr. 1 Died at the age of 71, Croton-on-Hudson, N.Y.
2005 Duke University Special Collections Gallery exhibition, James Karales: Photographs 1956-1969
2006 Kennedy Museum of Art exhibition, James Karales: Photojournalist
2013 Jan.-May Gibbes Museum exhibition, in Charleston, S.C.: Witness to History: Civil Rights Era Photographs by James Karales
2013 May University of South Carolina publishes Controversy and Hope: The Civil Rights Photographs of James Karales, by Julian Cox with Rebekah Jacob and Monica Karales and a foreword by Andrew Young.
Forthcoming James Karales, by James Karales, published by Steidl, texts by Vicki Goldberg, Howard Greenberg and Sam Stephenson.
Collection Overview
The collection spans the years 1953 to 2006 and houses a nearly complete photographic archive of well-known 20th century American photojournalist James Karales. The majority of the images in the collection originated from Karales' documentary work for Look magazine during the 1960s. The collection is organized around the following project series: Rendville, Ohio, a declining coal mining town and one of the first racially integrated towns in Appalachia; Vietnam, where Karales documented many scenes from the Vietnam War - the largest series in the collection; the Lower East Side, featuring street scenes and portraits from that New York City neighborhood; and Logging, where Karales documented the Pacific Northwest logging industry's practices and culture. Finally, Karales also shot many images of individuals and events of the Civil Rights movement during the 1960s, housed in three inter-related groups: the Martin Luther King Series; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) Series; and the Civil Rights Series.
There is also a small group of supporting materials in the Manuscript and Printed Materials Series and the Audiovisual Materials Series that includes biographical documents such as Karales' curriculum vitae; Karales' essays on photography and teaching; publicity for exhibits and other events; correspondence with publishers; digitized images of Vietnam photos on a CD; and clippings, magazine layouts, and other materials related to Karales' published work. One recently dated item is an audiocassette of remarks on Karales' life and works made by Sam Stephenson at the opening of an exhibit of Karales' work at the Rubenstein Library at Duke University.
Publications where Karales' works appeared include Look, Life, Saturday Review, Pageant, Coronet, Popular Photography, Time-Life books, and several encyclopedias. A number of Karales' images from the U.S. civil rights movement achieved iconographic status, and were - and still are - widely reproduced. The collection does not include Karales' photojournalistic work from East Germany (1970), or Gheel, Belgium (1961). Karales also produced photographs for corporate annual reports. His work is represented in the permanent collections of the Museum of Modern Art in New York.
Formats in the collection include contact sheets, which serve as a thumbnail guide to most but not all of the prints and negatives in the collection; black-and-white proof prints and finished prints ranging from 8.5x14 to 16x20 inches; original negatives (closed to research use); and several hundred color slides. Unless otherwise noted, the photographic items are arranged in the following sequence in each series: contact sheets, prints (from smallest to largest), slides, negatives, and finally, duplicates.
Beginning with the contact sheets, researchers using the collection can note any identifying codes for the image, which may include Karales' job number (Karales assigned most of his jobs or photographic projects alpha-numeric codes), roll number, and frame (image) number, in that order. Whenever possible, Rubenstein staff have included these numbers with individual prints and negatives and within the collection's inventory to aid in matching nd discovery. In addition, staff have noted where film rolls are located within folders. For finished prints (typically 11x14 inches and larger), individual descriptions and unique Rubenstein library identifiers (beginning with "RL") have been assigned. There are a few images that have no identifying numbers and could not otherwise be identified from contact sheets or negatives. Such captions appear in brackets.
In order to facilitate the use of the materials, please consult with a Research Services archivist before coming to use this collection.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Alabama -- Pictorial works
Appalachian region -- Pictorial works.
Civil Rights movements -- Alabama -- Pictorial works
Civil Rights movements -- United States -- 20th century -- Pictorial works.
Coal mining -- Ohio
Documentary photography -- United States.
Karales, James H.
King, Martin Luther Jr., 1929-1968.
Logging -- Pacific Northwest
Look (serial)
Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.
Montgomery (Ala.) -- History -- Pictorial works.
Pacific Northwest -- Pictorial works
Photojournalists -- United States.
Rendville, Ohio -- Pictorial works.
Selma (Ala.) -- History -- Pictorial works.
Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.).
Timber industry -- United States
Vietnam (Republic) -- Pictorial works
Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Pictorial works
Black and white prints
Gelatin silver
Negatives (photographs)
Slides (photographic)
Contact sheets
CD-ROMs
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Rendville, Ohio Series, 1953-1957, (5 boxes)
  These images are the results of Karales' first major photojournalistic work, a study of a small mining town in Ohio which was one of the first racially integrated towns in the U.S. Subjects depicted include adults and children, houses, local stores, miners, street scenes, and social gathering places such as churches and dance halls. Also includes images of Rendville's architecture, derelict buildings and landscape shots. In 1958, Edward Steichen bought some of the Rendville pictures for the Museum of Modern Art and Helen Gee exhibited the photographs at the Limelight Gallery in Greenwich Village, marking this photographic work as a breakthrough for Karales.
  Series includes contact sheets, small work prints, large finished prints, and negatives (closed to use), all black-and-white. Prints are all marked on the back with the photographer's original identifier and whenever possible are arranged in that identifier order, that is, in chronological order.
  - Rendville Contact Sheets, (8 folders, 114 prints)
    No job numbers have been identified for the Rendville photographic work. The 114 contact sheets include Karales' markings indicating images selected for proof prints or finished prints. Film roll numbers represented: 1-40 and 1A-5A. Of the 114 contact sheets, there is a set of 63 duplicate sheets.
    - Contact sheets: roll numbers 1-40, 1A-5A, and duplicates (Box 1)
  - Rendville Work Prints, (34 folders; 417 prints)
    Contains 52 4x6 and 365 5x7 work prints. Numbers represent rolls and frames, and are marked on the backs of the prints. Of the 52 4x6 prints, 29 are duplicates; of the 365 5x7 prints, 140 are duplicates. Folders are titled with the roll numbers housed within.
    - Work prints: roll numbers 1-18, 20-20; 1A, 2A, and 5A (Box 1-2)
  - Rendville Negatives Series, (50 negative folders)
    Approximately 250 negative strips representing film rolls 1 through 40 and 1A through 10A. Negative folders are labeled with roll numbers.
    - Negatives: roll numbers 1-40 and 1A-10A (Box 3)
  - Rendville Finished Prints, (32 prints)
    Contains 32 black-and-white gelatin silver prints selected from the thousands of images Karales shot in Rendville, Ohio in the 1950s. Some prints are mounted on board. All titles supplied by library staff.
    - [Man holding book before lower face, looking towards camera], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-001)
      Legacy identifiers: 3:34; GDC 2613
    - [Power cables in front of houses and field, just the right touch billboard], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-002)
      Legacy identifiers: 20:13; GDC 2693
      Same content as print RL-10017-P044 (16 x 20 inches).
    - [Family sitting on porch, blurred girl running from right], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-003)
      Legacy identifiers: 22:11; GDC 2685
    - [Two men talking on street corner, in front of church, side angle], 1953-1957, (8 x 13.5 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-004)
      Legacy identifiers: 23:4; GDC 2709
    - [Shot from porch to street corner, populated with two men and two boys], 1953-1957, (9 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-005)
      Legacy identifiers: 23:8; GDC 2700
    - [Speed limit 20 miles], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-006)
      Legacy identifiers: 24:12; GDC 2576
    - [Older man, close-up of face, left foreground], 1953-1957, (8 x 10 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-007)
      Legacy identifiers: 24:35; GDC 2757
    - [Two people playing cards in front of front porch], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-008)
      Legacy identifiers: 27:11; GDC 2551
    - [Three men shooting pool], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-009)
      Legacy identifiers: 28:28; GDC 2679
    - [Wooden door, overrun with lilies and grass], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-010)
      Legacy identifiers: 29:4; GDC 2604
    - [Two men sitting as freight train passes], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-011)
      Legacy identifiers: 29 34; GDC 2678
    - [Older woman passes decrepit building], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-012)
      Legacy identifiers: 35:4; GDC 2680
      Same content as print RL-10017-P046 (16 x 20 inches).
    - [Black girl in polka dot dress standing against building with younger boy], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-013)
      Legacy identifiers: 35:18; GDC 2539
    - [Working the kitchen garden, three people looking on], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-014)
      Legacy identifiers: 35:30; GDC 2577
      Same content as print RL-10017-P047 (17 x 21 inches).
    - [Working the kitchen garden, three people looking on], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-015)
      Legacy identifiers: 35:30; GDC 2661
      Copy of RL-10017-P014; same content as print RL-10017-P047 (17 x 21 inches).
    - [Two schoolchildren foreground, families in back, on road], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-016)
      Legacy identifiers: 38:26; GDC 2660
    - [Interior of church, preacher and congregation], 1953-1957, (9 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-017)
      Legacy identifiers: 40:unnumbered; GDC 2708
    - [Miner straining to place bit in horse's mouth], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-018)
      Legacy identifiers: 1A:4; GDC 2692
    - [Close-up of young child, striped shirt, looking to sky], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-019)
      Legacy identifiers: 1A:19; GDC 2681
    - [Steeply slanting barn roof, man walks down curving road], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-020)
      Legacy identifiers: 2A:18; GDC 2683
    - [Man standing in church, girl looks back], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-021)
      Legacy identifiers: 4A: unnumbered; GDC 2697
    - [Man standing, singing in church, shot from side front], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-022)
      Legacy identifiers: 5A:5; GDC 2698
    - [Woman clapping, eyes closed, left of frame], 1953-1957, (9.5 x 13 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-023)
      Legacy identifiers: 5A:6; GDC 2706
    - [Woman looking left, clapping in church], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-024)
      Legacy identifiers: 5A:10; GDC 2652
    - [Woman looking left, clapping and singing in church], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-025)
      Legacy identifiers: 5A:12; GDC 2659
    - [Pews of men and women singing and clapping], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-026)
      Legacy identifiers: 5A:14; GDC 2699
    - [Young boy, in suspenders, leans against telephone pole], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-027)
      Legacy identifiers: 6A:24; GDC 2684
    - [Woman playing piano, looking behind herself], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-028)
      Legacy identifiers: 7A:9; GDC 2696
    - [Side angle shot of porch], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-029)
      Legacy identifiers: 8A:5; GDC 2687
    - [Close-up of wooden post office boxes], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-030)
      Legacy identifiers: 8A:40; GDC 2550
    - [Woman sitting on rocker on porch, from the side], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-031)
      Legacy identifiers: 8A:41; GDC 2552
    - [Woman in rocking chair on porch, shot head-on, subject looking left], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-032)
      Legacy identifiers: 8A:42; GDC 2656
      Same content as print RL-10017-P049 (16 x 20 inches).
    - [Honest Snuff Welcome, close up of door], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-033)
      Legacy identifiers: 9A: unnumbered; GDC 2686
    - [Honest Snuff Welcome, close up of door], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-034)
      Legacy identifiers: 9A: unnumbered; GDC 2695
      Copy of RL-10017-P033.
    - [Interior room, furnace right, chair left], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-035)
      Legacy identifiers: 9A: unnumbered; GDC 2690
    - [Table with hat/scarf rack above], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-036)
      Legacy identifiers: 10A: unnumbered; GDC 2603
    - [Working the fields, kneeling man foreground], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-037)
      Legacy identifiers:; GDC 2575
    - [Front side of vehicle, wagon wheels], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-038)
      Legacy identifiers:; GDC 2622
    - [Older kerchiefed woman, arms akimbo, on winding road], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-039)
      Legacy identifiers:; GDC 2646
    - [Five overlapping barn roofs], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-040)
      Legacy identifiers:; GDC 2670
      Same content as print RL-10017-P051 (16 x 20 inches).
    - [Front of white church], 1953-1957, (11 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-041)
      Legacy identifiers:; GDC 2702
    - [Two men leaning against wall with eyes closed, shot from side angle], 1953-1957, (8.5 x 14 inches) (Box 24, Image RL-10017-P-042)
      Legacy identifiers:; GDC 2704
    - [A house engulfed in tree tops], 1953-1957, (16 x 20 inches) (Box 27, Image RL-10017-P-043)
      Legacy identifiers: 12 15
      Mounted.
    - [Power cables in front of houses and field, billboard], 1953-1957, (16 x 20 inches) (Box 27, Image RL-10017-P-044)
      Legacy identifiers: 20:13; GDC 2778
      Same content as print RL-10017-P002 (11 x 14 inches); mounted.
    - [Little girl in polka-dot dress, grasping a chair in dirt road], 1953-1957, (16 x 20 inches) (Box 27, Image RL-10017-P-045)
      Legacy identifiers: 20:27; GDC 2781
    - [Older woman passes decrepit building], 1953-1957, (16 x 20 inches) (Box 27, Image RL-10017-P-046)
      Legacy identifiers: 35:4
      Same content as print RL-10017-P012 (11 x 14 inches); mounted.
    - [Working the kitchen garden, three people looking on], 1953-1957, (16 x 20 inches) (Box 27, Image RL-10017-P-047)
      Legacy identifiers: 35:30
      Same content as prints RL-10017-P014 (11 x 14 inches) and RL-10017-P015 (11 x 14 inches); mounted.
    - [Interior, almost complete darkness, with men walking along track], 1953-1957, (16 x 20 inches) (Box 27, Image RL-10017-P-048)
      Legacy identifiers: 2A:5
    - [Woman in rocking chair on porch, shot head-on, subject looking left], 1953-1957, (16 x 20 inches) (Box 27, Image RL-10017-P-049)
      Legacy identifiers: 8A:42; Karales-p-01
      Same content as print RL-10017-P032 (11 x 14 inches); mounted.
    - [Side angle shot of young African American boy, standing flush against a power pole], 1953-1957, (16 x 20 inches) (Box 27, Image RL-10017-P-050)
      Legacy identifiers:
    - [Five overlapping barn roofs], 1953-1957, (16 x 20 inches) (Box 27, Image RL-10017-P-051)
      Legacy identifiers:; Karales-p-03
      Same content as print RL-10017-P040 (11 x 14 inches); mounted.
- Logging Series, 1958-1959, (7 boxes)
  Black-and-white images taken by Karales early in his career for a Weyerhauser lumber company assignment portray a full range of activities associated with logging in Oregon in the 1950s. Subjects feature individual loggers, logging crews and camp scenes, landscapes and aerial views of forested and logged areas, log driving, logging equipment, and logging activities on land and on a river. Identified geographic locations include Oregon (where apparently most if not all the scenes were shot), and Mt. Hood. The images are artistically compelling, featuring complex interplays of light and dark, and highlighting the placement of humans against natural landscapes and the giant trees they were felling.
  This series houses many "jobs" or photo shoots, to which Karales assigned an alpha or alphanumeric code. Print numbers consist of this code, roll number, and frame number. Prints are marked on the back with these original identifiers.
  - Logging Contact Sheets, (32 folders; 291 prints)
    The 291 contact sheets include Karales' markings indicating images selected for proof prints or finished prints. In some cases there are individual frames cut from the original contact sheets. There are six duplicate sheets for AE6 and duplicates for job E rolls 1-42. Folders in boxes are marked with roll numbers.
    - Contact sheets: Job AE6, rolls 1-33; Job C267940 (5 sheets, no rolls numbers indicated); Job E, rolls 1-70; Job AE, rolls 48-70; and Job WC/NE, rolls 116-164; and duplicates (Box 4-5)
  - Logging Work Prints, 4x6 and 5x7, (39 folders; 682 prints)
    Contains 33 4x6 and 649 5x7 work and proof prints. Numbers represent rolls and frames, and are marked on the backs of the prints. Folders in boxes are titled with the roll numbers housed within. There are seven folders of duplicate sheets.
    - Work prints, 4x6 and 5x7: roll numbers AE 1-67 and duplicates (Box 5-7)
  - Logging Work Prints, 8x10, (22 folders; 30 prints)